A Guide to the Papers of the Fortean Society, 1927-1952
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Fortean Society, 1927-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7657
This collection consists of 23 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 1964 August 20.
Scope and Content Information
Collection divided into three sections: Emma Goldman group, Fortean group, and Nietzsche group. The Emma Goldman group includes letters about Goldman including contributions by Theodore Dreiser, Eugene O'Neill, and Havelock Ellis to a fund to help her finance her memoirs.
The Fortean group letters are primarily concerned with society business, particularly problems with Tiffany Thayer and his prohibiting access to Charles Fort's notes and papers. The purpose and continued existence of the society is discussed.
In a letter to Arthur Leonard Ross, dated January 26, 1938, and not connected with the affairs of Fort or the Fortean Society, Edgar Lee Masters expresses surprise that he has been translated into Hebrew although Spoon River has been translated into Japanese.
The Nietzsche group includes correspondence about Nietzsche including discussions of copyright problems with Bennett Cerf. Also included is a printed page from "The Nation" of a book review by Alfred Werner of Nietzche's "My Sister and I" which discusses the probability it is a forgery.
Correspondents include Harry Elmer Barnes; Theodore Dreiser; Havelock Ellis; Charles Fort; Rockwell Kent; Edgar Lee Masters; H. L. Mencken; Eugene O'Neill; John Cowper Powys; Arthur Leonard Ross; Walter Starret; Booth Tarkington; W. S. Van Valkenburg; Alexander Woollcott; Tiffany Thayer and Burton Rascoe.
Contents List
- Emma Goldman Group
  - Theodore Dreiser to W.S. Van Valkenburgh 1927 Jun 19, ALS. 1 p.
    Check to help Emma Goldman advance her memoirs. Mentions publishers Boni and Liveright.
  - Eugene O'Neill to W. S. V. V. 1928 Feb 8, TLS. 1 p.
    With pencil notes not in Eugene O'Neill's hand. Will send check soon to help with Emma Goldman Memoirs Fund.
  - Havelock Ellis to W. S. V. V. 1928 Apr 16, TLS. 2 p.
    Sends money and a testimonial about Emma Goldman.
  - Havelock Ellis to Walter Starret 1930 Aug 6, ALS. 2 p.
    Thanks for the February issue of "Road to Freedom." Mentions Lenin and voluntary sterilization."
  - Rockwell Kent to Arthur Leonard Ross 1950 Dec 15, TLS. 1 p.
    Mentions Dr. Barr's pamphlet and recalls a banquet for Emma Goldman and a more recent one for Richard Morford.
- Fortean Group
  - Charles Fort to A. L. R. 1931 Nov 1, ALS. 1 p.
    Says that "The wisest thing I can say is that there really isn't anything to be wise about."
  - Theodore Dreiser to A. L. R. 1937 Jun 26, TLS. 1 p.
    Will not take action against Tiffany Thayer, former secretary of the Fortean Society. Says that Thayer has some notes of C. F.'s that should be in a publicly accessible collection, e. g. the New York Public Library. Mentions Ben Hecht and [David] Stern (owner of the N. Y. Post.) Dreiser mentions that he was denied access to the notes.
  - Alexander Woollcott to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 4, TLS. 1 p.
    Lent his name to the Fortean Society, thought its purpose was to call attention to Fort's book. Mentions that Mrs. Fort is suing Tiffany Thayer for the return of Charles Fort's notes.
  - Edgar Lee Masters to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 7, TLS. 1 p.
    Refers to the legal right to Fort's notes and papers. Masters says he "didn't know that I was ever a member of this society." Mentions Powys.
  - John Cowper Powys to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 12, ALS. 4 p.
    Shocked to hear of end of Fortean Society and that Tiffany Thayer is withholding Fort's original notes. Dreiser refused access also.
  - Booth Tarkington to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 19, TLS. 2 p.
    Fort probably not a member of the Author's League. Mentions Ivan von Auw, Jr. Discusses ownership of notes and letters of a deceased author.
  - Burton Rascoe to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 24, TLS. 3 p.
    Fortean Society was a phony organization, just a scheme by Tiffany Thayer to promote the sale of C. F.'s books. Mentions a dinner given by David Stern, publisher of the Philadelphia Record and later the New York Post, to promote Lo! Says only three members there, Thayer, Stern, Dreiser and self, mentions Booth Tarkington. Says the newspaper clippings are "so much trash" without Fort to make selective use of them. Makes reference to Swinburne, Theodore Watts-Dunton, Edmund Gosse, A. B. Paine, Mark Twain, and Twain's daughter, Clara Gabrilowitsch. Says that the Fortean Society was just a figment of Thayer's folly. Reiterates that Thayer can do what he likes if he is legally Fort's literary executor.
  - Theodore Dreiser to A. L. R. 1937 Jul 27, TLS. 1 p.
    Requests to see Fort's notes.
  - Booth Tarkington to A. L. R. 1937 Aug. 2, TLS. 1 p.
    Assumes that Fortean Society went out of existence at Fort's death. Says he was a member.
  - Theodore Dreiser to A. L. R. 1937 Aug 4, TLS. 1 p.
    Request to see Fort's notes but does not want a public row with Thayer.
  - Harry Elmer Barnes to A. L. R. 1937 Sep 17, TLS. 1 p.
    David Stern, Burton Rascoe and the Fortean Society.
  - Theodore Dreiser to A. L. R. 1938 Jan 26, TLS. 1 p.
    Requests to see the Fort collection, especially those in Thayer's library.
  - Edgar Lee Masters to A. L. R. 1943 Jan 26, TLS. 1 p.
    Surprised to hear that he had been translated into Hebrew - says Spoon River was translated into Japanese.
  - Tiffany Thayer to A. L. R. 1946 Jan 8, TLS. 2 p.
    Wishes all correspondence between Fort and Dreiser for the Fortean Society. Requests all the Aaron Sussman letters from Fort to be returned, as only borrowed by Dreiser for work on a biography of Fort.
- Nietzsche Group
  - H. L. Mencken to Ben [ ?] 1939 Apr 28, TLS. 1 p.
    Mentions dislike of Bennett Cerf. Says the Nietzsche copyright in America is imperfect. Discusses Dr. Oscar Levy.
  - H. L. M. to A. L. R. 1939 Aug 2, TLS. 1 p.
    Offers any help he can to aid Dr. Oscar Levy in his case against Bennett Cerf over the Nietzsche copyright.
  - H. L. M. to A. L. R. 1939 Aug 29, TLS. 1 p.
    Mentions that Dr. Levy has a publisher in England for his book.
  - The Nation"That Nietzsche Book" review by Alfred Werner 1952 May 31, Printed Page. 1 p.
    Discusses the probability that "My Sister and I," a posthumously discovered Nietzsche autobiography, is a forgery.